oh maybe i'll start uh with a simple one
uh i was reading about the abandonment
of the tendencies that we have towards
uh pleasant unpleasant and neutral
feelings and there was um i'm not totally clear
and there was um i'm not totally clear
on the tendencies that are supposed to
come from the neutral feelings
specifically it says
uh when one is touched by neither
painful or pleasant feeling if one
understands as it actually is the
origination the disappearance the
gratification the danger and the escape
in regard to that feeling then the
underlying tendency to ignorance does
not lie within this one
and this just confuses me
i i i i don't understand one bit of it
except that
it feels ignorance but
i'm not sure how the
the
well the the neutral feeling is the one
that's pretty much not seen
generally by people
um
it it's it's the it's the feeling that's
hardest to see for what it is as a
phenomenon that endures like oh it's
neither pleasant or unpleasant
people might have an idea about it but
they cannot actually you know it's easy
to see when you're feeling bad
that's obvious
it's easy to see when you're related
with pleasure it's obvious but what it's
not obvious is when it's kind of neither
and because it's not obvious that's why
that is felt unpleasantly because you
don't know it
so when people feel neither
they don't find that peaceful and
agreeable they find that there's a kind
of you know dull pressuring discomfort
so that's in in in the talks on on our
youtube channel i i did a few on that
and it is practically speech like
you know when you're bored how it starts
you don't feel bad
but by not feeling good either
and by not having any kind of
distraction to take your mind away from
it you start feeling unpleasantly
and um and that is still a neutral
feeling uh but because it's not known it's felt
uh but because it's not known it's felt
uh as a form of discomfort
so that we basically escalated uh on our
own from neutral to well unpleasant
afterwards well yeah
sort of but i wouldn't say escalate
because ignorance is already there with that
ignorance is already there with that
feeling because it's not understood so
there is no like a first point where
that feeling is clear and then you get
confused and then it escalates into pain
you already don't know it when it is
there which means pain is already there
without lack of knowledge
that's what the uh the sutas maybe even
the same sutra says when it's not known
it's felt unpleasantly when it's known
it's felt pleasantly by the wise they
find they understand that's where the
peace is
um so the ignorance is that not knowing
that not understanding
not being able to endure the pressure of
the neutral feeling seeking the
distraction out of it
all of that is what perpetuates that
ignorance it's not a it's ignorance it's not a
it's not a it's ignorance it's not a
lack of information or some you know
metaphysical secret or something
it's um not being able to endure the
discomfort of a neutral feeling acting
out of it seeking the distractions
perpetuating it feeding it that's that's
the ignorance that underlines it and
that you keep
sustaining in that very underlining
so when you do identify the neutral
feeling so for example the first
so for example the first
um
way to see it would be to recognize uh
let's say when you're bored on or when
you're looking for something like it's
not bad but
i could have something more
would that be a good way to yeah yeah
turn it down sure yeah when you have
nothing to do catch yourself before you
start doing something
and see like why is it that you want to
do it where is it rooted
or is it because you don't want you're
already trying to prevent the boredom
even before it it came so to speak
because often people always have
something to do lined up
and the the moment they sort of
the the moment they sort of
uh run out of things to do and calm down
they're already going for the next thing
which is not
you know often it's seen how i must do
this and this is this is necessary but
more often than not actually uh it's not
or certainly not as necessary
yet people have this um
accumulated pressure no no i still must
do this and they confuse that pressure
to be like a pressure of duty but it's
really pressure of escaping the boredom
oh well pressure of escaping the fear
that comes if you don't distract
yourself from boredom
because boredom if you sit with it it's
gonna become very unpleasant if you
refuse to do anything and just sit with
yourself it's it's gonna result in anxiety more
it's it's gonna result in anxiety more
often than not for people that haven't
been through that
so that's that's why when you kind of
relish the activity and and finding
things to do that you depend on
okay i remember hearing one of your
talks on what you challenged us to be
bored yeah intuit
yeah intuit
yeah like even even meditation practice
for people becomes something to do so i
don't get bored
okay thank you
i would actually have a question um on
meditation that's okay that's okay
um
namely the mindfulness of breathing meditation
the mindfulness of breathing meditation
this seems to be the most commonly
prescribed method of meditation
in various thumb attacks by various
teachers very popular and widespread
very popular and widespread
um but um
usually this instruction in these number
talks stops at stops at
the
feeling the breath coming in and out
of your body maybe feeling the entire
body some say feeling the body of the breath
some say feeling the body of the breath
but
reading the sutures you can see that
mindfulness of breathing was
much more elaborately described or this
instruction was much more elaborate
so there are such additional units to
this instruction such as
tranquilizing the body
experiencing rapture
experiencing pleasure
and then i'm also wondering about this
experience in the mental formations
um experiencing the entire mind and then
gladly concentrating and liberating the
mind and also contemplating permanence
trading racism
as well as
contemplating the elements
of of the elements so the four elements
plus space and
kindness and so the brahmani harness
so i was
i was wondering
um
do you think was this meant to be
like a step-by-step instruction on what
to do in one sitting
and in that case i don't think i will
remember all the motions when i have to
when i sit down and
or was it just
you know just general guidelines on what
kind of sentiments
um or i don't know little dispositions
to
to include in your meditation so
perhaps if we go back to the basics just
could you please
um
just give us some instructions on how to
meditate right how to
right how to
meditation of mindfulness of breathing
meditation uh well first you need to become a
uh well first you need to become a
sautabana
as the suit itself says
so
that's the something that everybody
seems to be overlooking and ignoring
the buddha told anapanasati to the monks
that were very much already on the path
were very much already on the path
and they haven't quite completed it so
he said oh well let me teach those who
still have work to do
which means it does not apply to people
they can't even have the sign of their
mind and have the right view it simply
doesn't apply it's going to be
misunderstood misperformed
misperformed
or is that other says mis-meditate
under-meditate over-meditate
pre-meditate everything else but not
meditate so really
so really
that should be the concern get in the
right view then
what samadhi is that would be known
through that right view
but just to answer your theoretical
aspects of
mana panasati no it's not meant to be
done as a step by step it's like the
most comprehensive
approach to the practice of mindfulness
on account of
and pretty much inherent inseparable
bodily activity
in every possible aspect they will
absolutely remove any traces of
ignorance left
but more often than not
monks were just you know doing it in
that in the broader sense how every
description starts knowingly he breathes
in knowingly he breathes out
and there was a there was another certified
there was a there was another certified
monk said oh that's how he practices it
and he abandoned sensuality of the past
sensuality of the future and sensuality
of the present he has no more central
desires because he has fully developed
breeding mindfulness of breeding on the
level of knowing glad britain knowingly
breathed out and then they would have
said yep that's fine but you should do
even more and then goes into those other
steps in other words that monk still had work
in other words that monk still had work
to do which on a subtle level which he
wouldn't have completed if he didn't
obviously refine further that microphone
and supreme
yes because it continues with the
entering the china's and it's uh
yes yeah
but again see that's that's the whole
like all of that follows on its own
all of that follows on its own
as a result of the right review
which means
it would be closer to the right
anapanasati say for somebody without a right view it
say for somebody without a right view it
will be closer for them uh to do the
meditation mindfulness of breathing
correctly not by watching the nostrils or
not by watching the nostrils or
breathing or following the steps but by
actually seeing the reason behind them
wanting to do it in the first place
why do i want to do this particular
mindfulness of breathing but what what
am i hoping for
where are my motivations rooted because
they're still there there will be
enduring there there will be the reasons
for your action the reason for your
effort so are you trying to gain something
so are you trying to gain something
as a result of it or are you trying to
undo that which already prevents you from
that which already prevents you from
having the right view
because right view is not gained right
view is uncovered
it's a completely opposite direction of
where people usually go for
so it goes against the stream against
the grain
um and that's that's pretty much the
nature of that knowing the motivation
behind your action it's it's behind the
grain of your action behind the
direction where you're heading to
um so whatever meditation you want to be
doing it's more important to know why
and what for
and don't just take you for granted
there's something that i must do because
buddhists meditate
and whatever comes out of it it will be good
whatever comes out of it it will be good
for me
because yeah
yeah
as as many suits say more often than not
people like that would end up meditating
with their own sensuality
which means
no good will come out of it
and that whole notion of well
concentration in itself is good
um
that's that's a very relative statement
like uh concentration itself is not a
good or bad it's just a state of mind
directed upon something
so it's the motivation behind that
directing that what determines your
intention basically as we spoke in the
last sunday
your intention determines whether you
know what you're about to do is rooted
in is good or not
is it rooted in desire aversion and so
on
so so the whole point is to recognize
that where the problem is that it's not
in in
what you're doing as much in terms of
meditation and what technique and how to
go about it
it's really on the level as to
what for and what are you hoping to
achieve with it are you clear you know
do you know exactly what this meditation
is supposed to result in or you're just
doing it
and then you're basically
hoping for some agreeable experiences
that will be of the spiritual kind
means there is no knowledge to begin
with yeah so you're just
chasing the novelties no not you
specifically just in general whoever's
doing it yes yes
um
actually i was
i was
reading super number 64.
mohammed
synthesis of everything also that you
just said basically because it's um it
distinguishes between the buddha
distinguishes between um you have the
two generals there you have the ordinary
person and then you have uh someone who
has been trained so i don't know uh arya
um
and the way he so so the thing is the
the way he so so the thing is the
question is how to escape for example so
how to escape from identity view so the
five lower letters among these also the
identity view
and um
and it's
and he says
um
when you teach the dhamma to someone
for the cessation of personality eu
then their mind must really enter into
this and the the first precondition if i
and the the first precondition if i
understood this
correctly is what you've been saying all
along this is seclusion from essential
pleasures this is the precondition for
them to even yeah
pleasure and unwholesome state yeah
absolutely yeah
yeah
so i like how you know the buddha goes
along to explain that whatever exists in
form feeling perception
formations and consciousness which is
basically everything there is right
everything that you can see
experience everything
everything
you must see
as impermanent
as causing suffering or
unsatisfactoriness [Music]
[Music]
yes and the only reason you need to see
these things as causing suffering is not
just like to torture yourself or cause
pain to yourself it's only because by
default they're seen as agreeable and
friendly while they're not
and there are other suitors where they
would have compares like you know your
own mind to like
basically um like an assassin that
pretends to be a friend but just really
wants to kill you
see the danger it is not in much in
effect that an assassin wants to kill
you the danger is in you thinking he's
your friend
if you stop thinking that he is your
friend he can't surprise you thus
doesn't matter how much of an assassin
he is you always see where he is
so the problem is not in the mind
wanting to kill you or the aggregates
want to cause you suffering the problem
is in your not seeing that because you
keep holding the view that they're
friendly they're agreeable that they are yours
they're agreeable that they are yours
you're yours exactly this is difficult
to say okay so you can see well yours
their scene is yours not as a choice
seeing them as yours is the result of
seeing them as friendly and
non-dangerous then
then
automatically they're taken as mine
so that's why you contemplate danger
just to the extent of not taking them as
mine and then you let the assassin be
and he can't surprise you and you're
fine
so would you say that um
by seeing how uncomfortable this all
the the discomfort that this causes all
of these forms feelings perceptions so
how much suffering there is in in those
um
aggregates uh uh
just
just by that
you can see like if it was really if it
was truly yours you would make sure that
it would be
pleasant at least yeah yeah you can
obviously you have to keep contemplating
that you have to keep reminding yourself of
you have to keep reminding yourself of
that
but before all of that your actions
must already be lined up with that
principle of oh this is not mine this is
not worth it
because often people would not have
sufficient amount of sense restraint and
guarding of the sense those and then
they try to contemplate this on top of
it but that's why it cannot take the
route or not as much
because their own actions are
contradicting what they are doing what
they are contemplating
so precepts sense restraint and guarding
the sense those that's the prerequisite
that really matches
what you're contemplating later
but you need to have it before yeah yeah
um
what would you say about this so turning
away so turn buddha says turn your mind
away from these states
turn them away
but then the next question is what do i
turn them towards so
where do i go then
should i direct my mind well no you you
don't turn it towards you don't turn it
towards a new thing you just turn it as
i said to the extent
to the extent that you were turned
towards this as friendly and acceptable
you turn away from that
friendliness and you don't accept it but
you don't acquire a new thing now
because that will become your sense of
self again
so you turn away to the extent that you
will turn towards it
but you don't turn away to find
something new
because then your mind will become
established upon that
right so pull your attention back back in well
so pull your attention back back in well
see you put your attention back and
you'll be attending that yeah
yeah
it's going to become another thing
you're looking at
i mean your own question imply that
what do i turn it towards as in there
must be something i must attend to
how do you disperse that
that spotlight potentially well you
can't disperse the attention because
that's part of the aggregates but you
can know the context of it
the context right yes but you don't
attend it you don't make it into another
object or when you do you at least don't
lose the context of that
right so again that's on the level of
the knowledge
like things that you know even in
mundane terms
like whatever you know your knowledge
basic basic knowledge that you have in
regard to things
you don't need to constantly be
attending that on a day-to-day basis in
order to remember it not at all quite
the opposite you need to attend things
when you don't know them
when you actually get to understand them
you stop it you stop thinking about it
you stop attending it and when that
knowledge is needed it comes back
because that's what understanding is
and it goes the same for the dharma
practice when when that man asked the buddha oh
when when that man asked the buddha oh
does the target does he prepare these
answers to the various questions that people ask
to the various questions that people ask
him and he said well let me ask you in
return and that shall give you the
answer you are the master charioteer in
making of the chariots do you if
somebody comes and asks you about
various parts of the chariots do you
need to prepare the answer
or do you know it right away he says oh
i know it right away if somebody were to
wake me up in the middle of the night
i will know the answer anyway because i
i am the master of cherry i fully
understood the principles behind how it
works how it's made and the word i said
so it's the same for the targeter so he
doesn't need to prepare the answer
because he fully understood it
so knowledge really just knowledge of
the universal characteristics of your
experience cannot be undone and cannot be forgotten
cannot be undone and cannot be forgotten
and that's why it results in liberation
not perfect attention hundred percent
undivided never never never kind of
sways no that's the basically unenlightened
no that's the basically unenlightened
mind idea of what the enlightenment is
full absorption into something that's
outside of me that will save me
basically
so actually it's the same thing in
the instructional meditation that i was
asking about before
because the buddha also says all breaths
are known yeah
knowingly he breathes in
knowingly he breathes out
he breathes in feeling his nostrils or
sensations in his chest
i mean you know you're already breathing
why do you need more why is that
knowledge not enough to your mind well because of
not enough to your mind well because of
your wrong assumptions
so really the training of the mind is to
recognize what it already knows
and realize
that that it's enough that knowledge is
enough if you sustain it and protect it
and the training of the mind is not
basically to to sort of develop
experiences on its own terms but what
the mind deems agreeable and so on
because what the mind deems agreeable is
sensuality of one kind or the other
and this knowledge
during meditation or during whatever
activity this knowledge
also will solve you know all the other steps
will solve you know all the other steps
will self-generate the rapture will
self-generate pleasure will sure be
there if you sustain it sufficiently
enough develop your mind becomes
imperturbable then yes everything else
will follow that's what i said before
that's what you said before and now yeah
these two stupas are very much
interconnected and this everything else
is cool it really comes down to to sort
of curbing the tendency
to to follow the steps and find the next
steps at the expense of that which you
already know
see everybody who sits down to practice
everybody who sits down to practice
meditation breathing knows that they are
already breathing
but that ceases to be enough to mind
stops noticing it and wants something
more palpable
i want the feeling of of lightness i
want nostrils to feel i want the lungs
why is the knowledge not enough why is
the knowledge so abstract when it's
actually quite factual because the mind
is not trained to recognize that level
for what it is
mind is dependent on more palpable
things because mind has been acting
towards the sense objects its own life
so that's the measure of its existence
the senses
so that's exactly why even the basic
knowledge even as an instruction
it's not people no but tell me well tell
me the steps tell me what i observe and
what motions i do because anything
subtler than that is felt like an
abstract theory yet they know that
they're breeding at any given time
there's nothing more factual than that
with knowledge this knowledge of being
this knowledge of
yeah
is the peaceful this is the sublime and
this is what you actually in fact then
turn away
yeah you can say that that knowledge
will basically turn your mind away
from things that it shouldn't have been
well it shouldn't have been there in the
first place that's it
that knowledge will prevent you from
from um
regarding those things as friendly
agreeable and as yours
and i find this very useful here
buddha says
be aware that space is infinite if your
weight or space is infinite there's not
not much place for thoughts there
there's not much place for perceptions
for nations consciousness anything
anywhere so it's like the mind
completely expands
uh she's talking about the deathless
element there and that the consciousness
is infinite
so this is how
it expands and i also like that he says
there is nothing
i like that
there isn't anything yeah he said there
is yeah
he said that nothingness is something
to that extent it is it is a phenomenon
the absence of certain things so it's
nothing it's emptiness and all of these
negative sort of phenomena are positive
in themselves for what they are
it's not a mystical experience it's just
factual empty of lust empty of aversion
empty of delusion
before we continue to the next topic i
just wanted to check if i understood
something correctly so when i was
reading i don't know it was it the same
suit or a different one i don't know
but there was um
it said
um as they're breathing in and breathing
out they
think about
different things and the way i saw it
the the breath was just a trigger or
mindfulness so it's something that you
always have with you
and every time you notice that you're
every time you notice that you're
breathing it can like remind you that
you need to stay in the moment and not
perhaps uh you know
um
go to too far away with your mind
so
the way you understand it
it's a reference point it's like an
anchor so so
ah
the breathing is always there
as i said in other talks
underneath your thoughts your feelings
everything else you're concerned about
or related about underneath all of that
this body is still breathing there
so knowledge of that
is what anchors you from being too
driven too far away in those thoughts
and forgetting
where the anchor is
because it doesn't matter so much about
wondering how you're breathing and how
it feels like it's just
no no no not at all no it's knowing that
you're breathing
knowingly breathes in knowingly he
breathes out
if that's fully developed
to the extent that it can be developed
all those other steps
will become apparent and follow out of
that okay that's my answer thank you
very much
um
yeah we have a question here could you
please say something about the role of
faith in democracy
um yeah so faith in dharma practice is
as i said many times before it's like
faith you need to have in a doctor
that you think he might be able to help
you if you have absolutely no faith
if you have absolutely no faith
in what the doctor says
you won't even try the medicine that he
prescribes so but equally if the medicine is not
so but equally if the medicine is not
working
you don't need to have faith in that
doctor because you saw that his
instruction didn't work
that's when you change the doctor so
it's not a blind faith that you must
remain faith full of faith towards the
end like for the rest of your life
it's the faith that you can be helped
in terms of the dharma practice
and that faith should then be practiced
out of and eventually replaced with the
knowledge that yes this medicine worked
and i'm healed i don't need to have a
faith in this doctor anymore because his
medicine worked and now i'm confident
that it was the right instruction
that's why in the suit as a person who
gets the right view their faith gets
replaced as how the colleague of
confirmed confidence
now they know for themselves that the
medicine works because they can see
themselves healing
but it's certainly not the faith that
would be on the level of
oh i have faith the buddha was the
greatest and i'll be saved on account of
that faith like you know what in
christianity is often found
mind you in buddhism it's often found
so it's the faith that should make you
practice that's it
okay we have another question
this one is
what exactly is right you and how do you
get to the right view
keeping the precepts seeing the danger
in the fault guarding the sense
those uh being moderate in eating
uh being moderate in eating
avoiding company living in seclusion uh
and that will make you notice your mind
for what it is
and when you do
it won't be too hard to see it as
something that doesn't belong to you
and that would be the right review
so impermanent suffering and non-self
this is these are yes people think i
must see that
and having not fulfilled all the
requirements before that they were not
going to see it
if they have fulfilled all the
requirements before that they will see
it even if they don't make much effort
to see it
i was reading a little bit uh about
non-self uh as well
and um
well some things are very clear like um all
some things are very clear like um all
the things you should not consider as
self but then that leaves us with the
but then that leaves us with the
question what remains so if we take all
of this away
the the guidelines the the criteria that
were stated um
whereas so something that is permanent
and something that we have control over
so
what in your opinion would be
then qualified to be called self
qualified to be called self
i don't quite understand so what is
permanent and what do you have control
over so uh in one of the sutas it said so if
so uh in one of the sutas it said so if
things are impermanent they cause
suffering and therefore should not be
considered as a self or mind and then
similarly it said uh if things were mine
then i would have control over them and
since i don't have control over them
they are not mine so
and the many different sutures say a lot
about all the things that are not self
yeah i was wondering what remains
nothing that that's the cool point
that that's the cool point
there's nothing worth being calling
himself nothing worth owning
because if you do to that extent you
will be liable to suffering
that's the whole nothingness practice
but for example if
if i think
um who i am
i think about all the choices
uh i made
in my life that led me to this point so
at any at any point in life i could have
made a different choice and i
i would have become a different person
so if i consider these choices all the
past choices
don't they fill this criteria i mean
they're permanent once they're done they
are done
you cannot change them
and you have control over them you might
not have the control about the
circumstances you are in sure you have a
degree of control but did you have a
choice did you have choice in the
options that were presented to you that
you chose from
no exactly that's the circumstances
exactly so your choice of control is
always second to the circumstance
so it can never be the control of
ownership because it's always within
that which you cannot own
so the choice you have it's like a
choice of
driving a car down the cliff you can
choose to turn left and choose to turn
right but you can't stop it
so nobody denies that there is a
phenomenon of control and choice but you
want to include that in that which is
not liable to your choice which cannot be
liable to your choice which cannot be
penetrated by your choice in your
control and that's exactly why i asked you for
and that's exactly why i asked you for
the options yes you chose this on
account of this but did you have a say
in what arose for you as the options of
choosing no and you never will
so even the the permanence of the choice
is only relatively within the
impermanence of the options okay so
it would be foolish to say that
anyone has full control over it but
couldn't we define ourselves relative uh
to to the situation
or would that
suffer the difference
the difference
you can define yourself in a relative
way but that's not the problem nor the point
but that's not the problem nor the point
the point is that
any form of definition will kind of
feed the assumption that to to the
extent that there is a control
are to that extent your sense of self is
justified but see if you see it
correctly as a relative thing
like sense of self is not seen as a
relative even if you talk about it in theory as a
even if you talk about it in theory as a
relatively risen or formed fundamentally
sense of self is the owner and the
master of this experience but what kind
of master is a relative master
only a deluded master would say i'm a
master ignoring his own relativity
because if he is relative he is not in
control thus he is not the master and that's all
thus he is not the master and that's all
you need to see you don't need to
destroy that sense of relative self
or deny it or find something greater you
just need to disown it completely and
leave it be
okay i'll i'll have to think on that but
thank you
uh just a quick note uh would you say
that this self-determination or
self-definition it is sort of a constant and very fast
it is sort of a constant and very fast
exercise in
accumulating and
and combining memories
exercise is performed by whom
it happens it happens really fast um
in cases of
where you came from so it has to be a
whole story behind the self
it has to be a story where it came from
where you are now the decisions that
you've made the things that you've done
and well all of that is unified already
well all of that is unified already
by the center self
it happens
very fast so i believe this happens
really fast in
in our minds
every every regaining of consciousness
every regaining of consciousness
um
this very slight moment where the the
memories fall back into place as mosaic
peace
no well see how can you know then
the moment before that happens
because the moment before that happens
everything is blank
so what are you saying the blankness is
then the truth
no the blindness is just the blankness
so how do you know that how do you know
that that blankness is not owned what
makes you think that it's not owned
it's too empty to be owned
nothing to call hold on to then you have
to have the first memory and then stack
them all up
but again see the blankness is already a
memory so what you call a first memory
it's not a first memory blankness before
that is a previous memory
so what is then the first memory
it's an infinite loop that's why it's
impossible to see what you're referring
to
blankness before the memory can only be
known as a memory thus it's a
contradiction in terms
suppose you wake up
you know you've had a slight case of
amnesia wake up
you have no idea
just no idea
sure so you're like a newborn baby yeah
the memories then then okay this is
where i came from this is what i did
before that
and then it snaps up really fast and
there it is
it's your personality there again okay
everything now i can function
okay but say say like this say you wake up
but say say like this say you wake up
from amnesia and your memories don't
come back
yeah so what do you think that state
after indonesia is that state pure or is
that state equally corrupted you know
and or based on ignorance and ownership
and not seeing impermanence
yeah i think it's i think it's just by
no means anywhere near enlightenment and
so that brings us exactly to what we
said memories and your sense of self
that came out of it it's relative and
remains relative
so whether you remove it whether you
erase the memories whether you catch the
first moment before the memories that's
all of that is already owned that's
where the buddha said that even like the
new born baby
that doesn't have the memories has not
developed central appetites has not
corrupted itself the mind the senses are
already underlined by all the um
astavas by by the uh tendencies
underlying tendencies towards sensuality
towards craving towards views which
means it's not a question of catching
the first moment
and then the second moment the question
is abandoning the whole picture
the whole thing because
you can just see that it's just it's
conglomerate yes but it's irrelevant
whether it's a conglomerate if it's a
one thing if it happens very slowly if
it happens very fast happens within the
framework and it's the framework that
needs to be abandoned and framework is
not happening very fast framework is
there from the moment you're born
yeah that's always there yeah so that's
the point that's how many memories you
accumulate and if you're trying to
forget or undo all of that is second to
the problem
the problem is underlying tendencies
towards ownership
that are pretty much manifested they
start from the beginning as i said baby
has no sense of self
that has developed on a kind of choices
and so on yet it keeps acting out of
these underlying tendencies which is why
it develops the sense of self
that's why i keep saying the sense of
self is not the problem
it's the symptom of an underlying
problem acting out a pleasure pressure feeling
acting out a pleasure pressure feeling
acting out of neutral feeling acting out
of uh
uncomfortable feeling
sense of self will be generated one way
or the other
so if you zoom in
if you really explore what's happening
there at that level look at the tanha
behind us this magnetism
really zoom into that
no no no no you need to zoom out
framework zoom out context not zoom in
the opposite direction that's what i'm
saying it's not about catching the
moment before or after it's about
zooming out far enough to see the
framework there
and that's where tonka is
well you see that
in
zooming out as well maybe you will
because it's probably
that's the only place you will see
it's tanka it's not a momentary response
tanha is basically the whole
direction of your mind already on the
level of that framework okay
okay
maybe we're talking about cross-purpose
purposes here i i was thinking of um
exploring a certain emotion
really feeling it really going in there
into that
the feeling really exploring exploring
it from within
and at a certain point you will feel
this this humongous pull
this humongous pull
the pull of personality
and when you feel like you're no i think
we're talking about the same thing but i
keep trying to point the opposite
direction of what you're saying
see you don't explore the feeling by
getting into the feeling
that basically means making it even more
particular which means falling away from
the nature of the feeling absolutely you
need to zoom out
okay so instead of going to feel it more
you zoom out to know it more know what's
already there
whichever way it's all there you don't
need to make it felt differently to get
to understand it better
whichever way it's felt you want to know
it to that extent that's the framework
i'm talking about so it's the opposite
of falling onto the particular level
it's staying on that general the
background i often talk about
and that's where the thunder is
okay next question yeah
yeah
thank you again for uh your willingness
to give this question an answer
this is something that
is quite interesting to me namely
to what degree if at all it's even
possible to
meaningfully talk about self
within the buddhist framework
because from what i've heard from your some of
from what i've heard from your some of
your talks it's not
some people have this very
i would say simplistic understanding of
what non-self is supposed to be
often it is understood either as a
simple negation of the self or they go
down the humian line where they think
that basically it's more or less a
mosaic of you know uh
of you know uh
uh aggregates and then they say well
there's no south because
in every moment of experience of these
constituents so if you break this down
this is who i am but this this is just
um
i would say a very
experientially naive way of
thinking about it
but the thing is for instance when i was
uh reading the suta
uh
all the things he ends up with a list of
basically all the views that are wrong
with regards to the self
so all the views that arise from um
sensual desire being an ignorant
and can i read them out surely
can i read them out surely
okay so he says
these are the six views that arise in
someone who
basically is ignorant if we over
simplify self exists for me
self exists for me
no self exists for me
i perceive self with self i perceive not
self with self i perceived itself with
not self and everlasting enduring so
yeah so everlasting enduring self okay
let's put this aside let's say that you
know for the most part even in most of
say western thought nowadays there will
be very few people who would be willing
to adopt some view of this type
but the other views are either present
with everyday experience or in most of
philosophical accounts that you would
find for instance you might say
um
someone like
kuster would say that you know i
perceive self with self so you have a
transcendental self that perceives the
the empirical self or many similar might
say okay well this the transcendental
self is not really a self it's a non
self sort but all this is wrong so i'm
just curious you know
there would seem that there is a certain
place for the self so to speak it is
naive to say that non-self is simply a
negation of
you know
the self
in in some strong sense so i would just
be interested as to how would you
suggest one goes about
reflecting on the self and what would
you say
the term the notion this of the self
designates uh or
or
whether this is even you know something
that could be articulated i'm not
particularly keen on the idea that it's
not in the past i would be but now this
would be for me somehow
a cop-out of sorts
if you have any thoughts on that
well yeah there is self
it's not yours that's it so the buddha
never said there is no self
he said that which itself is not yours
and there's a big difference
so it's removing the ownership
it will remove the sense of self people
people think i own things because i am
no it's other way around
it's because you keep taking things as
mine through sensuality aversion and
ignorance that's why you are
that's why you have generated that sense
of self that you cannot not step outside
of it's a symptom
it's a symptom of ownership you remove
the ownership center self cannot persist
or not to the same extent
that's why artavada is a view
see there is a sense of self as a result
of careless ownership
not seeing impermanence
not restraining your actions
and that self that has been generated
through such actions
you put first and that's the attawada
you think that is the first thing
so i own things because i am
no it's because you keep owning
individual things that's why you are
that's why that sense of self is there
and that's why the view on top of it is
there so it's not a
you don't develop the experience of not
myself through figuring it out
through figuring it out
you develop it through purifying your
behavior that has been feeding it and
sustaining it
and then you'll see that that sense of
self does not belong to you and thus it
cannot be called self truly
that's when people came to the wood and
said ah so master gautama says there is
no self and he would be quiet he
wouldn't he wouldn't even reply to that
because it's a completely well it's a
question completely based on that wrong
assumption that they don't see
uh so there is a sense of self then
master gostimate no he wouldn't he will
reply to that either
but practically speaking
that sense of self that is yours
remove that part of this is mine and it
won't be sense of self anymore but don't
try to remove the whole thing by saying
oh the self doesn't exist
if it doesn't exist what are you
referring to
as non-existing
there has to be something that's being
designated when people say oh there is
no self
and that's that whole the the view
permutation with self he is his self
of itself he sees not self
or with not self he sees self but
putujna cannot with not self see the not
self it has to be sense of self has to be
it has to be sense of self has to be
either on the immediacy level on or on
the level of reflection
but if he were to undo the ownership
of any kind through contemplating
impermanence sensor strength guarding of
the sense those
then he will be able to see not self
with the note self in other words
without owning the sense of self he can
see that self which is there
which won't be self anymore
so the ownership part is what makes it
the self not that thing that it's there
taken to be the self
because when the buddha said what is it
that you know putujna takes herself oh
it's the form it's the feeling it's the
perception it's the intentions and the
in the consciousness there is nothing so
all the phenomena generally
your sense of self will be resting upon
something because your sense of self
will be resting upon the ownership of
something so
so
if i understand correctly if
you remove this ownership you also
remove the
attachments you have to it to it
and therefore you would see it more
therefore you would see it more
objectively is this the difference
uh sort of it's basically if you say you
know you keep eating food that doesn't
agree with you
and your whole body is suffering you're
having headaches and who knows what else
and you don't know the reason you don't
know that it's because of the food
so now you you sometimes you have a
headache like this but if you
concentrate on something else headache
disappears then you think maybe but
either way you keep eating the food that
it's making your condition worse then
you find out that that was the problem
you stopped eating the food that was
bothering you
sufficient time needs to pass basically
until the body recovers and the headache
will slowly dissipate and not come back
and that's what will happen to the sense
of self
not that you're gonna lose your head
that used to hurt
you're just gonna lose the pain of that
which still remains there
so that sense of self that sense of an
individual that's still making choices
that remains
but the emotional uh ownership of it
that's gone and that is another hand
that's where people cannot unders think
all either cannot understand or think
arahant is this
spaced out robot unaware of himself
no he still makes choices he still
prefers he still has agreeable and
disagreeable he has no ownership of any
of it top to bottom
and that's why he cannot suffer because
he's not involved with the wrong view
would you say that this
so this is
something i really suggest i thought it
was really nice
the sense of self is actually a
corruption of the mind
it's a corruption
so
mind the mind without the self
sense of self
the buddha says it's malleable wielding
and radiant
sure sure but see if somebody is not
free from the sense of self
their thought of a mind that's malleable
radiant is taken as their self in other words
is taken as their self in other words
that's not what that mind is
so then now you you are perceiving the
idea of not self mind free from self
reach your current self
and that's one of the views that that's
read out
so you cannot even theoretically
understand mind free from the sense of
self free from the ownership unless you
have developed non-ownership here and
now i received another question very much
i received another question very much
related to this so the question goes if
nothing is yours
what is then your mind
if nothing is left
how do you train your mind or what do
you train your mind with
would you mean nothing's left
everything is left
you haven't touched anything
you just removed your gratuitous
emotional ownership of it
you don't need to destroy things to not
own them
you just need to stop regarding them as
yours mentally
because if they are not yours they're
not your problem
exactly now imagine you have that attitude
now imagine you have that attitude
towards your own senses towards your own
feeling towards your own intentions
towards your own mind imperforable
attitude in other words you cannot
forget that it cannot be yours even if
you want it to be yours it's important
inconceivable ownership becomes
inconceivable because you thoroughly understood
because you thoroughly understood
the danger the peril the escape and so
on the impermanence the unownability of
these things you're fully understood and
you can you don't even need to keep
telling yourself oh this is not mine
so nothing can disturb you then at all
absolutely inconceivable suffering or
any perturbance cannot be even perceived
anymore
great i don't trust saying i'm sorry
maybe i
i
said somewhere um
every time so you have these problems
the phone keeps ringing and every time
the phone rings you pick it up and say
hi this is mr smith and
and he said well just stop picking
picking up the phone and stop thinking
you're mr smith
yeah well you can't help you can't stop
thinking who you are
yeah it's not a matter of choice but you
can certainly stop uh owning how mr
smith feels and not acting out of the
feeling when you pick up the phone
and then even that mr smith will fade
away
so could you in a certain sense say
because this act of ownership is
interesting could you say then that
could you say then that
maybe one way of putting this would be
to say to to realize that the the
structure of the cells so or the sense
of self
is something that is embedded
on a
in a larger picture in a larger process
which is basically
selfless so there's already this uh
sense of so so the act of ownership the
pro the process of ownership right
because there's a there's a slight
potential danger here you might say that
well you know where is this sense or
process of ownership nested
so who is it that wants to own
right uh
that's a problem so in a certain sense
you kind of have to realize that this is
a bottomless process so to speak it is a
process that does not have yet another
cells underneath it that would like to
grasp or yeah in that sense it's beginningless
or yeah in that sense it's beginningless
it's it's like like a vicious circle
i mean like you have a headache
because of the food you eat and you keep
eating the food because you think it
suits your headache
so headache is not a problem it's a
symptom but at the same time
becomes a problem because you keep
acting out of it
stop acting out of it it's going to be
seen as a symptom and then eventually
you're going to discover what the real
problem is you kept thinking that's the
problem and you kept acting out of it
and you kept doing things they were
feeding it in return ironically enough
in the buddhist perspective so the
overall general framework the question
as to how and why this came to be is a
known question so to speak exactly it's
a question of like when good is said
imagine a man being shot by an arrow
yeah but instead of allowing that arrow
to be pulled out and and wound healed he
won't allow it until he finds out who
shot him
why they did so what did he do to
deserve that
is there anything that he could avoid
what clan was the man that he all of
these irrelevant things while he's dying
so you need to realize where the
priority is getting the arrow out
doesn't matter who why or what shot me
what matters is i'm shot and i'm
bleeding out
okay i would have a question uh if
or would you want to say something
no i was just trying to fill the the
silence with some random ramblings so thank you
with some random ramblings so thank you
we just said that we're not supposed to
do that uh
uh
yeah so i i'm just
i've been really interested in uh this
notion of uh
yoni somana sikara
it's first of all i find it fascinating
how basically for example in the west
you know just one particular notion sati
became the main focus of interest and it's all
the main focus of interest and it's all
about mindfulness and everything is
mindfulness can i just sorry
can i just sorry
can you also explain the word because i
don't know some of these foreign words
and then i just lose the track of the
yeah don't worry that was that was the
general idea so uh
i didn't want to just jump in this is
just a preface or background so uh
what i meant is to say even if at this
point uh
nobody knew what this term meant is that
there are a lot of very interesting uh
fascinating terms and notions in in in
the polycon and i found it just
fascinating how uh one of them was taken
out and it's now just
all all the rage
but um with regards to yoni sumana
sikara
so if i understood correctly yoni saw
refers etymologically to the worm for
work for a womb yeah
and it is usually translated as wisely
or properly
yeah and
a literal translation would be mental
act or
or
mentation so to speak
meditations yeah
but it is often translated for some
reason as attention
so
uh
i i listened to a talk you gave on this
and i wanted to re-listen it this week
unfortunately was unable to so i would
just want to first of all uh hear your
how would you translate it because
if i remember
correctly you translated it as wise
reflection which i think is closer
when i was reading specifically
i might have mentioned it but i don't
think i would translate a wise
reflection no no okay it would be
attention or rather attending from the
origin let's say like that
again it's it's a subtle thing whichever
way translates you're going to have to
be explaining it
it's not going to so it's not going to
become self-evident on account of your
choice of the terms you use for it
because it's too subtle to be understood
it's one of the prerequisites for the
right view
so it's a hard thing to clarify for for
every mind individually
but it's exactly that if you stop and
think about it
you always you know people always
approach things by attending to them
that's oh okay so i look at this i think
of this i perceive this
womb of that act is what the only so
many so the origin
but see if you attend to the womb now
of the origin
that becomes the thing you're attending
to which means the womb of that
attention is again behind you
is again behind you
so it's learning to see that behind
without attending it how can you do that
by knowing it
that's why
context background peripheral awareness
all these things i'm talking about it's
all that it just points at the same
thing and that's where the knowledge is
and and that's why it's so
important to realize
that all the rage and mainstream
practice it's completely misdirected
it's completely based on perceiving and
seeking and seeing and particularizing
more and more and more
all that's irrelevant
all of that is finding more details at
the expense of the context that you
don't even know to begin with
and if you do you wouldn't need any of
the i don't need to know what shape the
arrow was and how it flew and the
physics behind it
all i need to know that is that hurts
here and now and i'm resisting the pain
that's it
that's the detail level that you need to
have you don't need to know anything else
so it's a tendency to not just attend
but to over attend and attend even more
what you attended to so then when you
tell them no it's the origin of the
attention ah so they attend to that it's
like yeah but now there is something
else as the origin of that attention
so how can you know it without attending
it
and that's that's the whole practice of
learning how to see it peripherally
because that's what the experience is peripheral
that's what the experience is peripheral
and actual
whether you attend to it or not that is
the basis for your attention
like whatever you're attending now on
account of your senses is possible
only because your senses in the form of
this body
are still there
simultaneously with what you're
attending to yet you're completely
unaware of them
so learning to be aware
without needing to attend to the senses
because that's impossible
learning to know that there is an eye
as an organ eye
necessary basis for all the sites you
are concerned with
but if your measure of mindfulness
is what you attend closely you'll never
develop this mindfulness how can your
eye attend itself
well by looking in the mirror well no
you're attending to the reflection of
the eye
for which presence of the eyes necessary
you remain equally unaware of the
context and that's the only sumanasika
and that's the only sumanasika
discerning that which cannot be attended
yet it is there is a necessary basis
is what that wise attention is
and the problem with wise or proper
attention it's not that it's
etymologically wrong to translate like
that but the problem is people will
think all right so i am engaging with
the practice of yoni sumanasikara when i
stop and think about things
no
or certainly not necessarily
so if i just think about things a bit
more that's what the buddha meant by
yoni sumanasikara which is a
prerequisite for soto party
no it's a bit more than that
it is precisely
for this reason because of what you've
just described that i found this idea of
reflection or the term reflection so
useful you know precisely this notion
where you have you're not engrossed in
the object that is given to you but
you're basically trying to capture the
whole setting of it so the dynamics of
intending you're trying to capture the whole
you're trying to capture the whole
setting
like the alertness the german word they
highly used
without making it an object that's the
key because
because
even heidegger made it an object
because that's the tendency of the mind
you see the context some people more
some people less
but then you take that for granted and
that becomes your object and you lose
context in regard to that
so yes you want to capture the setting
without attending it
so it's all about it's not about finding
the first context or the first original
object or something it's about fully
purifying and clarifying and removing
any slightest traces of the ignorance of
the relationship between what you're
attending at any given time and the
necessary basis for that attention
that's it you understand with this this
is
all the object is undone but teaches
them about the fulfilled completed
with the presence of this this is
with the presence of the body as the
base for the senses
there is sight this is what i'm looking
at because the body is there
so knowing that relationship
fully understanding it
that's what needs to be done
if we go now back to what we were
talking before about the the breathing
meditation could we say that in a
certain sense for example when you have
mindfulness uh of breath and the body in
general what you're basically doing is
precisely going to the very
let's say in a certain sense foundation
the very basis
on which you can basically build this
because it's
in a certain sense you're kind of going
as as deep as you can go
uh with the dynamic with this dynamics
that you were mentioning because breath
as a living as long as you're alive
breath will be there the body posture
will be there so there is always like
you know uh
uh embodied intentionality so to speak
towards something that is given yeah
you're kind of um
getting familiarized or acquiring
knowledge of this background all
pervasive background and then you can
see yeah for as long as it stays the
background that's the point
because it's too easy see to start
attending to the breath and the body as
an object of your attention which means
it's not a reference on a background
level anymore
but yes
if you know it as being there
while experiencing this or knowing it as
being there while experiencing that
you are practicing seeing it as a
reference and standing your mind in that
knowledge and then yes you don't need more than
and then yes you don't need more than
that that's what would have said all
these different you know sati patana of
this mindfulness of that or he's mindful
of the body to the extent necessary for
the final knowledge just that so to the
extent necessary you have fully
understood this context extent necessary
for uprooting of passion aversion and
the need for distraction and ownership
and that's it
so
the question would be i i could
completely uh yes so so i find this very
helpful uh but the question would be
would it be right to say that as an
intermediary step so to speak you make
something that is implicit explicit so
that you actually know it so what i mean
by that is everybody in a certain sense
know that he or she breathes right you
have to make it in the sense that you
become aware and that you understand and then
aware and that you understand and then
you you you move it into the periphery
but the quality has changed yeah if if
that's what you are told you're supposed
to do
but people are told the opposite you're
supposed to attend it even closer
and even closer and catch even more
specific sensations
if they were not told to do that there
would be no problem
initially whatever you do you have to do
it by attending it first
but if the knowledge of the peripheral
is there
you won't be confused in regard to that
that's why arahant still has attention
and he still attends and choose and as i
said prefers and so on
but there is no more
perverting of the order and confusing
and putting the second first and so on
that's impossible
this is great i mean this this has been
uh of uh tremendous help for me in my
practice hearing your talks on this on
these ideas so this was also very useful
now to be able to check something
i think we have quite a few in that as
well i'm probably saying the same anyway but
i'm probably saying the same anyway but
yeah
um
okay so gaining the right view is what
what this group and everyone should be
striving for
yeah gaining
right to you and then then we'll be able
to understand everything else
yeah then you will know what you need to
do to be fully enlightened
you also hear accounts of uh some other
teachers such as i don't know advise the
teachers claiming that they have gained
the right view
and what some of them are saying seems
seems correct seems uh seems right
um do you think so um according to the
suttas once you get the right to you
it's a matter of life times a few
lifetimes before you actually gain
enlightenment so if you gain the right
view in your previous life
um probably that's what's going to
happen then you're going to it's going
to be easier for you probably in this
life
i wouldn't use the word easier
you're just probably gonna have less
polluted relationship with your own
suffering so you're gonna arrive at certain
so you're gonna arrive at certain
conclusions quicker
but you're gonna suffer equally because
you're still born
yeah yeah i didn't mean in terms of
suffering just uh it seems that some
some of these
some of these individuals
seem to be saying
saying it correctly or yes but uh but
they're not even in the buddhist
tradition and
and
probably just this the first step the
right view
is probably not so much
well yeah i don't really know what
they're saying so i can't say no they're
all wrong or yes they're right
but on the individual basis on the basis
of what's being said i can tell you
whether that's along the right lines or
not many teachers say oh just be here now in
many teachers say oh just be here now in
the present moment that's all you have
and then you read the sutras oh they
look the suta say the same yeah on that
superficial level it sounds the same
but what else do those teachers say and
what else did the suit say how do you go
about it
tell me more like oh doctor says he can
cure me this doctor also says he can
cure me great i have options
but you don't stay there now you go
start talking to the doctor and see what
you need to do but if the doctor starts
saying some genetic nonsense
and doesn't even really just gives you
so oh well and then well you already
know trusting that because surely if you
understood the how to approve the illness you would
the how to approve the illness you would
know how to do it
and that's often you'll find that you
have all these various eclectic teachers
that collect
you know all sorts of like buddhism and
other religions and it does all sound
same on that level you know when
somebody's at the bottom
they can't see the difference between
you know halfway up the mountain and top
of the mountain because it's all just
one direction up there it all looks high
anyway but there is a difference once you start
but there is a difference once you start
walking it like how far you can go with
it
and and you don't want to ignore that
just because now it feels right
or you don't want to dismiss it either
just now because it doesn't necessarily
feel right you want to know what's
behind okay what's more to this
instruction and same if the instruction sounds wrong
and same if the instruction sounds wrong
you want to know why it is wrong not
just oh that's wrong because ajinamali
said so
well do you know for yourself that
that's wrong for such and such reason
why is that inadequate
yeah there doesn't seem to be much
instruction behind these claims that's
the problem then thus claims cannot be
taken like you should not take them for
that's the whole point you are making a
claim towards the cure
and they're not saying how to cure
yourself means you don't know what you're talking
means you don't know what you're talking
about means your doctor who just
pretends to be a doctor doctor who just
mystifies the solution but has no no
actual solution for it
and you read the sutras and it's
completely the opposite it tells you
exactly what you need to do
and by the way it's same not just for
other religions
and if you hear monks speaking giving
instructions talking about the cure
talking about the cure
find out how to go about it from them if
they can't tell you means they don't
know it as simple as that
because if a person knows the cure he is
absolutely it's inconceivable to not
share it with you when he's talking
well the only thing he's talking about
is the cure
but i will not tell you how to do it
there's absolutely no reason for that
it's unfinished
there's nothing out there there's nobody
doing anything so that's why i can't
tell you anything because there is
nobody here saying anything nobody
listening exactly so basically
trying to convince you that you're not
actually sick
although we started this conversation on
account of mutual illness
now my solution is to teach you how to
delude yourself into believing you don't
even have a headache what is a headache
anyway
and that's always the pinnacle of most
of the stuff i heard it's well
there is no problem anyway stop making a
problem there is no problem
if they were the solution you would have
needed one suitor that says that and end
of story
yeah but see many people would still
think oh yeah that's also what the
buddha teaches yes it's completely earth
and sky opposite things
so the packaging sounds the same inside
completely different thing
but if you're judging things only on
account of the packaging you're never
going to find this up
uh i have a follow-up question uh to the
earlier one earlier one i had
so
if i
a boredom is one of the things that is
challenging for me it's
i'm a very active person and i feel that
there is something i could learn from it
and it's quite easy to decide
okay not easy but at least doable
to decide i will not
talk i will not walk i will not actively
do things
i i will not watch tv i will not go for
a walk i'll just sit here this is uh not
trivial but easy but how how do you deal
with your mind because i find it very
easy to distract myself
with my mind alone you know you can
start thinking about memories you can
start making plans plans are
one of the big
ways to describe practically
maybe you don't have to do it on such a
rigid level to begin with
i will not walk i will not move
but instead choose on the level that you
can sustain
for a longer period of time
such as
i won't switch the tv on look at my
phone leave the apartment but i'll move
around drink tea sit about i won't sleep
i won't read i won't distract myself
but i'll stay here and then the mind
will obviously start thinking about
various things initially but spend three
or four hours maybe longer like that
the mind will stop and then you will be
back to where you are
so in other words
you start rigidly and then you
immediately also want to fix the mind to
not think about things within that
limited framework because you can't
sustain not moving and sitting and not
going out and not doing anything for too
long so find something you can sustain so
so find something you can sustain so
that mind can calm down within that and
that's it then you'll see it
okay to go more gradually about it and
yeah exactly yeah so there's no problem
if you're moving about
the problem is when you're doing things
on account of restlessness on account of
being bored and so on and again
and again
walking around back and forth in your
apartment can provide you only so much
entertainment initially
after very quickly you'll be bored with
it so keep doing it
that's what these repetitive actions
like walking meditation is good
yeah oh
i don't want to walk because i'm
restless no no walk you can't be too
distracted by walking up and down the
same lane
i can go for hours just walking and
thinking you know
making plans and things like that that
is well if if that's what you're
actively doing then you can't say you're
not doing anything you're actively
making plans so then don't do that but
if the mind still keeps popping up with
things that's fine that will calm down but you
that's fine that will calm down but you
also have to stop fueling it oh yeah
i'll think about this i'll think about
this i'll think about this because you
do have that choice
whether to think about what mind
presented you with or not
so you you just like dropped the ball so
you know when your mind throws you an
idea you you don't hold on to it and you
say okay yeah and when the master where
the mind throws you the idea you don't
delight in it you don't welcome it but
you don't deny it either
because see the people
don't want to stay in that kind of state
of in between mine pops up with stuff
and i'm enduring not giving in so they
want to prevent the mind from popping up
with stuff
and that's usually meditation techniques
come for that purpose so i can stop
thinking because thinking is the problem
no
it's you being moved by the thinking
that's why there is a problem not not
the thoughts
but for as long as you think the
thoughts are the problem you're
mistaking the symptom for the for the
root for the root cause
for the root cause
so don't try to prevent your mind from
coming up with this stuff but certainly
prevent yourself from accepting it
and that's the work that's the endurance
and you don't need to endure
self-inflicted torture and hunger and
sleeping on the nails and whatever else
to develop your mind you just need to
endure these very things that you have
on your day-to-day basis
mind throwing stuff with you and you're
just blindly catching it and accepting
it and following it along
don't do that and you will be training
properly
okay thank you
i would just have a
short question uh on the daily practice
and it's uh just the the feeling i got
from some of the things that you said
would it be correct to say that you are
not particularly
keen on say
suggesting to anyone who started
uh
being involved with buddhism
to have like this daily meditation
a routine
i got the impression that uh
you would prefer to suggest that they do
something else instead you can have a
you can have a meditation routine i
would just not agree to the type of
meditation people are doing
oh okay i wouldn't agree to what they
call meditation to be
but yeah you can like routines are
useful certainly in the beginning
but it's like what you perceive
to be a duty that's where the problem is
and that's exactly the thing see people
i must meditate you know because of this
because of that all of that is rooted in
them still not knowing why they're doing
it in the first place so that should be
a meditation
knowing the intentions behind your
actions developing the context so
so
the reason why i sometimes bring up this
question about the reflection and
discussivity and whatnot is because for
me personally
it was extremely liberating where i at a
certain point allowed myself to actually
um
bring more
reflective and discursive activity into
my meditation right because it somehow
seems that this is like forbidden
sure but
when at a certain point for instance i
can give a concrete example when when um
a very unpleasant
feeling arose during meditation
instead of my trying to either focus on
it
or focus on the breath
i
started asking questions such as what did what
asking questions such as what did what
would it mean for you
if this
feeling persisted for the rest of your
life yeah yeah that's it
and that was the actual meditation part
see you broaden the context with a
simple question aimed rightly
and by the way the suttas are full of
that like mahmoud alana before he
developed jhana the meditation of
meditation how he developed it like observing the
how he developed it like observing the
souls of his feet or nostrils or no he
developed it by sitting down and saying
first jhana first jana what is the first
jhana well the buddha said it's this
this this and this
how about i think about all those things
and fully understand him and by doing so
he entered and abided in first gen
thinking and pondering
basis for other hundreds as well
yet today perception is
focus concentrate ignore cover up shut
down
yes precisely and i think that this is
uh
it's really important to
to kind of dispel this this notion this
idea yeah
again for me it was
every now and again you would have in
different fields or spheres of your like
these qualitative shifts for me it was
something that simple that
no i know because you know like i
started also as a layman
like really just any form of buddhism i
really just any form of buddhism i
didn't know right from wrong in that
sense uh but in hindsight i could tell then
uh but in hindsight i could tell then
what things were along the right lines
and which one weren't
and i was very dutiful when it came to the
i was very dutiful when it came to the
meditation routine out in the morning
out in the evening it didn't matter
every day
if i had to work or whatever else
and i thought that was my duty
but in hindsight i realized i would have
been better off if i didn't do that and
did other things that i didn't know were
my duty but fortunately did them so for
example like i
like i
would fulfill my duty of of meditating
for an hour in the morning in the
evening and then go out with friends
i would still keep the precepts
that was not the issue but it would be a
fun time
men women company all of that
and i felt fully justified in doing so
because i fulfill my duty of meditation
and hey i'm still keeping the presets
well in hindsight i realized i would
have been better off if i didn't spend
two hours watching the nostrils and if i
didn't go out with the friends
that's it
and all those times when i didn't go out
like that for the sake of entertainment
or distraction that's why i could then
see later on that's where i benefited
from not that i knew it but i kept doing
it because it felt right
it felt like giving to the weakness
otherwise but nobody told me that that was right
but nobody told me that that was right
thing to do
it's kind of okay you assume but no the
right thing is to watch your nostrils
and observe your movements and touching
touching feeling feeling sitting sitting
and everything else
and you take that as a duty and it's
completely misguided utterly
but if somebody told me no don't do any
of that
but every single day
of your life
be aware
for the motivation
behind your actions and don't act
towards lust aversion and distraction
doesn't matter what it is
it would have saved me so much time as
well
and then if you want to sit quietly and
think about wholesome things that's fine
and make a routine out of it that's fine
but that's where the benefit is and
that's where the work is oh but i
fulfill my duty i can go out you know i
can i can i can enjoy this i can enjoy
it you can but that's why you're not
progressing in the practice
and you realize okay so that's where the
emphasis should be
not on this misguided duty of observance
of sensations of your body or something
that you won't find in the sutures
either way
yes this uh this resonates very well
with me because
it it was um
it's almost as if
there's this idea almost as if uh
as if meditation was some sort of a
syrup that you take yeah then it kind of
does its own thing it's like a mechanism
exactly you set it in motion and i don't
know what's going on yeah and then you
just get these results just it just does
the thing yes
yes okay thank you very much a lot of
things to be said here but maybe we save
some for next time